Guide to the Judy Malloy Papers, 1956-2010
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Judy Malloy papers 1956-2010
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Malloy, Judy
15.6 linear feet Extent: 13200 Items
Judy Malloy is a poet and an early creator of online interactive and collaborative fiction. She is a founder of the Arts Conference on the WELL, and wrote Uncle Roger, the first online hyperfiction. Collection includes documentation and materials from Malloy's publications and programs, including Uncle Roger and its name was Penelope, as well as materials from her nonfiction research, including her 2003 book, Women, Technology, and Art. Also includes exhibition files and correspondence files from Malloy's career as an artist, both from creating artists books and from her work in new media and hypertext. Correspondence files include letters, postcards, original artwork and clippings from other artists as well as electronic literature (e-lit) artists and writers.
RL.10044
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research, but original electronic media is restricted. All disks have been removed from the collection for preservation.
However, collection may contain materials to which the Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibilities and Privacy Rights form applies. Patrons must sign this form before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 24-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Judy Malloy Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2010 and 2011.
Biographical Note
Judy Malloy is an artist, poet, and early creator of online interactive and collaborative fiction. She is a founder of the Arts Conference on the WELL, and wrote Uncle Roger, the first online hyperfiction.
Chronology List
1942 January 9 Born Judith Ann Powers, Boston, Mass.
1977-1993 Created and exhibited numerous artists books
1986 Began writing and programming Uncle Roger
1989 its name was Penelope exhibited at Richmond Art Center
1990 its name was Penelope published by Narrabase Press
1991 Programmed and produced You!
1991-1993 Editor, Leonardo Electronic News
1993 its name was Penelope published by Eastgate
1993 Began working for Arts Wire
1993 Became Xerox PARC artist-in-residence
1994 Created Making Art Online website
1995 Created Forward Anywhere with Cathy Marshall
2003 Editor, Women, Art & Technology, published by MIT Press
Collection Overview
The Judy Malloy Papers includes the personal and professional papers and materials from Judy Malloy, a groundbreaking artist, author, and poet working in electronic literature and online interactive formats.
The collection is still being acquired, with new additions being regularly added to this finding aid. Please consult Research Services with questions about this material.
Malloy's Printed Materials series includes both books and journal publications, with content both by and about Malloy, as well as some of her own reference material. Many books feature a chapter or contribution by Malloy, discussing or explaining her experimentation with online narratives and electronic fiction. Other articles discuss and reference her early contributions, including Uncle Roger and its name was Penelope. Some material relates to computer programming and early Internet research material. Finally, this series contains a cluster of books used by Malloy in her research for various publications. These are grouped at the end of the series.
The Notebooks series includes Malloy's notes and drafts for her various writing projects, including Uncle Roger, its name was Penelope, and Brown House Kitchen. These notebooks reveal the changes each work underwent as it was edited and outlined.
The Early Artists Books series consists largely of notes and photocopies of some of Malloy's early books, as well as a folder with color slides of a selection of her art.
Malloy's Writings and Programming series is largely focused on her new media work, with large amounts of material from her creation and publication of Uncle Roger, the first electronic hyperfiction. These files include her original work, as told on the Art Com Electronic Network (ACEN), as well as later versions and program printouts. Similar documentation is available for its name was Penelope, originally exhibited by Malloy in 1988-1989 and eventually published by Narrabase Press in 1990 and Eastgate in 1993. This subseries also includes an artist book for Penelope. Smaller amounts of materials exist for Malloy's other e-literature and programs, including You!, Brown House Kitchen, Molasses, Forward Anywhere, Wasting Time, Thirty Minutes in the Late Afternoon, Dorothy Abrona McCrae, and Paths of Memory and Painting, among others. There is also a small amount of material relating to Malloy's printed works, including Women, Art & Technology, as well as early children's literature.
The Exhibitions series includes documentation and materials from Malloy's installations and exhibitions of her artists books as well as exhibitions of her new media and electronic fiction. These have been divided thusly in the Detailed Description, and subsequently arranged chronologically. Materials include postcards, plans, correspondence, news clippings and press coverage, contracts, and other materials relating to the exhibit.
Talks and Readings is a small series with materials from various speaking engagements. The most significant was Malloy's participation in the Telluride Ideas Festival in 1993.
The Correspondence series includes much more than correspondence, and is in fact more of a name file of Malloy's relationships throughout the artist and e-lit communities. Her general correspondence includes letters from her childhood and college travels, as well as some miscellaneous files of correspondence with various curators and others regarding her exhibitions. The bulk of the series, however, consists of Malloy's artist correspondence and Art Com Electronic Network correspondence. These files include letters, postcards, prints, news clippings and press coverage, and occasional pieces of original art sent to Malloy throughout the 1970s and 1980s. The ACEN artist files include email and letters, some exhibition documentation, and some software-related documentation that overlaps with the Media by Other Artists series. The Correspondence series is grouped by General, Artists, and ACEN Artists, and subsequently sorted alphabetically.
The Media by Other Artists series includes software and accompanying documentation by several ACEN artists, many of whom included inscriptions or autographs for Malloy, as well as other new media. Finally, the Personal Materials series includes a subseries of personal photographs and slides, information on Malloy's family, and memorabilia including calendars and documents.
RESTRICTIONS: It should be noted that while this collection includes electronic media, these disks have been separated from the manuscript material in order to be migrated to Duke's Electronic Server for preservation. If you are interested in accessing this material, contact Research Services in advance.
Subject Headings
Malloy, Judy, 1942-; Malloy, Judy, 1942- Uncle Roger; Malloy, Judy, 1942- Its name was Penelope; Hypertext fiction; Women authors; Hypertext fiction -- History and criticism; Artists' books; Artists books -- Exhibitions; Art Com (Firm); Floppy disks; Artists -- United States -- Correspondence
Separated Material
Electronic disks have been removed from the collection and are housed in the Separated Digital Media Collection. Contact Rubenstein in advance if you are interested in these materials.
Contents of Collection
- Printed Materials, 1940-2010, (8 boxes)
  Printed materials including books and journals with articles or poetry by Malloy. Also includes her computer programming books and manuals, reference materials for various projects, and some items that reference her and her work, along with a subseries on Arts Wire Current/NYFA Current, a magazine that Malloy edited from 1996-2004.
  - Books
    - Apple II DOS Manual, 1980 (Box 1)
    - SupraExpress modem manual, 1996 (Box 1)
    - IBM Basic Handbook, General Programming Information, 3rd edition, May 1984 (Box 1)
    - Stephen Levy, Hackers: Heroes of the Computer Revolution, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Kacsmer, The Easy Guide to Your Apple II, 1983 (Box 1)
    - Craig Harris, Art and Innovation: XEROX PARC Artist-in-Residence Program, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Marshall McLuhan, Understanding Media, The Extensions of Man, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Gregory Battcock, New Artists Video, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Howard Gardner, Creating Minds, 1993 (Box 1)
    - J. Dawn Mercedes, Feminist Aesthetic Theory as an Alternative Aesthetic Paradigm for Computer-Mediated Art (Dissertation, The Ohio State University), 1999 (Box 1)
      Malloy's work discussed, pages 93-98.
    - Heide Hagebolling, ed., Interactive Dramaturgies: New Approaches in Multimedia Content and Design, 2004 (Box 1)
      Includes Malloy, Writing Public Literature in an Evolving Internet Environment, pages 181-189.
    - Net Art Guide, 2000 (Box 1)
      Includes Malloy's work, The Roar of Destiny, pages 44-45.
    - Institute for Studies in the Arts, Arizona State University, The Simulated Presence: A Critical Response to Electronic Imaging, Feb 1993 (Box 1)
      Limited edition fine press book. Includes video. Malloy's work is discussed and illustrated in Text 4: Linnea Dayton, Interactive Fiction: Past, Present, and Future.
    - Sol LeWitt, Sunrise and Sunset at Priano, 1980 (Box 1)
      His work was influential on Malloy's card catalogs.
    - Peter D'Agostino and Antonio Muntadas, eds., The Un/Necessary Image, MIT Committee on the Visual Arts, 1982 (Box 1)
      Includes Malloy's Anyway you look at it, ADM has your antenna..., pages 76-79. Article is documentation of Technical Information, Malloy's 1981 installation. Folder includes review of the book.
    - Cliff Pickover, ed., Visions of the Future, 1992 (Box 1)
      Includes Malloy's Electronic Fiction in the 21st Century, pages 137-144. Folder also includes edited draft with notes from Cliff.
    - Lynn Cherney and Elizabeth Reba Weise, eds., Wired Women: Gender and New Realities in Cyberspace, 1996 (Box 1)
      Includes Malloy and Cathy Marshall's Closure was Never a Goal in this Piece, pages 56-70.
    - Judy Malloy, ed., Women, Art & Technology, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Richard Stallman, GNU Emacs Manual, 5th edition, October 1986 (Box 2)
      Also includes some correspondence with Richard.
    - Suzanne Foley, Space Time Sound Conceptual Art in the San Francisco Bay Area: The 70s (Box 2)
    - Lew Thomas, Photography and Language, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Lew Thomas, Structural(ism) and Photography, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Robert Haas and Jessica Fisher, eds., The Addison Street Anthology, Berkeley's Poetry Walk, 2004 (Box 2)
      Judy Graham's work is signed, page 132.
    - Jean Radford, Dorothy Richardson, 1991 (Box 2)
    - Jack Kerouac, San Francisco Blues, 1995 (Box 2)
    - Gugliemo Achille Cavellini, Autoritratti, 1981 (Box 2)
    - William T. Wiley, Honest Lies Somewhere Between, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Howard Rheingold, Tools for Thought, 1985 (Box 2)
      Includes inscription for Judy Malloy.
    - John Quarterman, The Matrix: Computer Networks and Conferencing Systems Worldwide, 1990 (Box 2)
      Includes second folder with information on the Cultures in Cyberspace virtual panel.
    - Christine Maxwell and Czeslaw Jan Grycz, The New Riders' Official Internet Yellow Pages, 1994 (Box 2)
      Includes part of an inscription from Christine Maxwell. Malloy was a primary paid consultant on this book.
    - Yoko Ono, Grapefruit, 1970 (Box 8)
    - Stephen Wilson, Information Arts: Intersections of Art, Science, and Technology, 2002 (Box 8)
      Wilson and Malloy met at CADRE in San Jose in the 1980s and were colleagues in the Xerox PARC Program. Malloy's work is discussed on pages 487, 525, 563, 594, 688-689, and 828.
    - Spalding Gray, Swimming to Cambodia, 1985 (Box 8)
    - Jerry Crimmins, A Visitors Guide to La Republique de Reves, 1980 (Box 8)
    - David W. Kritt and Lucien T. Winegar, eds., Education and Technology: Critical Perspectives, Possible Futures, 2007 (Box 8)
      Includes Malloy, Approaches to Creative New Media, pages 151-157, and a mention of the chapter by the editors on pages 10 and 263.
    - Ursula Meyer, Conceptual Art, 1972 (Box 9)
    - David A. Kaplan, The Silicon Boys and Their Valley of Dreams, 1999 (Box 9)
      The prologue explains the role of Woodside in Silicon Valley culture; see Uncle Roger, File I, A Party in Woodside.
    - Peter D'Agostino, TeleGuide, Including Proposal for QUBE, 1978 (Box 10)
    - Bruce Breland, The Digital Art Exchange: A brief history 1982 until the present, 1994 (Box 10)
    - State of the Arts, the Proceedings of the Electronic Literature Organization's 2002 State of the Arts Symposium, 2012 (Box 24)
      Includes Malloy's "Writing and Interface on the Contemporary Internet: A Public Literature."
    - Terri Cohn, ed., Pairing of Polarities: The Life and Art of Sonya Rapoport, 2012 (Box 24)
      Includes Malloy and Anna Couey's "A Conversation with Sonya Rapoport (on the Interactive Conference on Arts Wire)."
    - Lillard, W. Huston, Courage on the Danube, 1964 (Box 24)
      Malloy's grandfather's self-published account of his work as Chief of Resettlement of the International Refugee Organization, 1946-1947.
    - Allen Ginsberg, Howl, 1974 (Box 27)
    - Palmer, Michael, Company of Moths, 2005 (Box 27)
      Autographed.
    - Snyder, Gary, and Tom Killion, The High Sierra of California, 2002 (Box 27)
    - The Uffizi: Catalogue of All the Works in the Gallery (Box 27)
    - Books used in connection with Women, Art & Technology and the associated website (Box 1)
      - Art-Reseaux, Ouvrage Collective Projet Art-Reseaux (coordination with Karen O'Rourke). A CD version is also included. (Box 1)
      - Joan Jonas, interview by Robin White at Crown Point Press, 1979 (Box 1)
      - Sherry Tuckle, Life on the Screen, 1995 (Box 1)
      - Nancy Patterson, Mediaworks, 2001 (Box 1)
      - Brenda Laurel, Utopian Entrepreneur, 2001 (Box 1)
      - Mary Anne Moser, Immersed in Technology: Art and Visual Environments, 1996 (Box 1)
      - Donna J. Haraway, Simians, Cyborgs, and Women: The Reinvention of Nature, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Books used in connection with Paths of Memory and Painting (Box 9)
      - David Stick, Roanoke Island: The Beginnings of English America, 1983 (Box 9)
      - Brian Swann, ed., Native American Songs and Poems: An Anthology, 1996 (Box 9)
      - Kim Shuck, Smuggling Cherokee, 2005. Signed edition. (Box 9)
      - Rita Coolidge, Laura Satterfield, and Priscilla Coolidge, Walea (CD), 2002. Includes the Cherokee version of "Amazing Grace" that was sung on the Trail of Tears, which is mentioned in Dorothy's Arioso in The Wedding Celebration of Gunter and Gwen (Paths Part III). (Box 9)
      - Charis Wilson Weston and Edward Weston, California and the West, 1940 (Box 9)
      - Arnold Skolnik, ed., Paintings of California, 1997 (Box 9)
      - Early Artists of the Bohemian Club, 2002. Essay by Ann Harlow and catalog of exhibition at Hearst Art Gallery, Saint Mary's College of California. (Box 10)
      - Flyers and posters, Hearst Art Gallery, Saint Mary's College of California. Materials concerning landscape painting exhibitions and the William Keith Collection. (Box 10)
      - Nancy Boas, Society of Six, 1997 (Box 24)
      - William Keith, The Saint Mary's College Collection, 1994 (Box 24)
      - Obata's Yosemite, The Art and Letters of Chiura Obata from his Trip to the High Sierra in 1927, 1993 (Box 24)
    - Books used in connection with the Dorothy stories
      Books on California Bay Area figurative painting were used for background research for Dorothy Abrona McCrae and more directly in Paths of Memory and Painting.
      - Thomas Albright, Art in the San Francisco Bay Area 1945-1980: An Illustrated History, 1985 (Box 10)
      - Caroline A. Jones, Bay Area Figurative Art 1950-1965, 1990 (Box 10)
      - Susan Landauer, Elmer Bischoff: The Ethics of Paint, 2001 (Box 10)
      - Karen Tsujimoto and Jacquelynn Baas, The Art of Joan Brown, 1998 (Box 10)
      - Footloose in Arcadia: Artists and Authors of the Piedmont from 1890 to 1930, 2007. Catalog of exhibition at Hearst Art Gallery. Saint Mary's College of California. (Box 10)
      - Here and Now: Bay Area Masterworks from the Di Rosa Collections, 1994. Catalog of exhibition at Oakland Museum. (Box 10)
      - Baum, L. Frank, The New Wizard of Oz, 1944 (Box 24)
  - Journals
    - View 2:3, June 1979 (Box 11)
      Interview with Terry Fox by Robin White.
    - High Performance 8:1, 1985 (Box 11)
      Includes Spalding Gray: Traveling Through New England, Swimming to Cambodia, pages 28-32 and 87-88.
    - Beatitude 33, 1985 (Box 11)
      Silver Anniversary Issue. Inscribed to Judy Malloy by cover artist Byron Hunt.
    - Whole Earth Review no. 57, Winter 1987 (Box 2)
      Includes Malloy's Information as an Artists Material, pages 48-49
    - Leonardo 21:4, 1988 (Box 2)
      Includes Malloy's OK Research/OK Genetic Engineering/Bad Information, Information Art Defines Society, pages 371-375.
    - Roy Ascott and Carl Eugene Loeffler, eds., Connectivity: Art and Interactive Telecommunications, Leonardo 24:2, 1991 (Box 2)
      Includes Malloy, Uncle Roger, An Online Narrabase, pages 195-202. Also contains thanks from Carl on page 113.
    - Action Poetique 129/130, Winter 1992-1993 (Box 11)
      Corresponding KAOS disc included in Software.
    - Leonardo Words on Works pages, edited by Malloy, 1992-1997 (Box 2)
    - MicroTimes articles, 1993 (disk removed) (Box 2)
      Articles by Malloy include: Artware-Intelligent, Responsive Works of Art are Changing our Ideas about Art, February 1993. Art Online, A Look at Artists, The Arts Community, and Collaborative Artwork in a New Medium-Electronic Networks, March 1993. Manipulating Words with Computers, November 1993.
    - Leonardo 29:4, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Special Issue on Technocritism and Hypernarrative, Modern Fiction Studies 43:4, Fall 1997 (Box 2)
    - Arts Wire Current, 1997-2002 (disks removed) (Box 11)
      Issues edited by Malloy; copyright free before it became NYFA Current in 2003.
    - Leonardo Electronic Almanac 11:12, December 2003 (Box 11)
      Printout of special issue on Women, Art, and Technology, guest edited by Judy Malloy.
    - Leonardo 38:3, 2005 (Box 24)
      Includes Malloy's "Streaming Media Trail."
    - Grantmakers in the Arts GIA Reader 21:2, Summer 2010 (Box 2)
      Includes Malloy's Travels with Contemporary New Media Art.
  - Arts Wire Current/NYFA Current, 1993-2003
    Arts Wire was founded in 1992 as an online computer network intended to facilitate discussion and collaboration among artists. Malloy began working for Arts Wire in 1993 and was editor of its ezine Arts Wire Current (which became New York Foundation for the Arts [NYFA] Current in 2002) from 1996-2004.
    - Arts Wire News, 1993-1995, and NYFA Current, 2002-2003 (Box 22)
    - Articles about Arts Wire, 1994-2000 (Box 22)
    - Arts Wire documents, 1994-2004 (Box 22)
    - Malloy essay, "Memories of Arts Wire," and email correspondence to Malloy from subscribers and contributors, 2001-2004 (Box 22)
  - Troy Innocent and Dale Nason, "Cyber Dada Manifesto," November 1990 (Box 11)
- Notebooks, 1981-1989 and undated, (1 box)
  Spiral notebooks with Malloy's notes from planning art installations, as well as separate notebooks with character development, plot structures, and programming notes for Malloy's works Uncle Roger and its name was Penelope.
  - Technical Information show, SITE, 1981 (Box 3)
    Includes small photographs of the card catalogs and other artists books in the installation, as well as installation notes, floor plans, and instructions on creating the installation.
  - Early work, 1985 (Box 3)
    Includes art notes, as well as a photograph of Malloy photographing an art work.
  - Uncle Roger, 1986-1987, (3 folders) (Box 3)
    5 notebooks with notes from the writing and programming of Uncle Roger. Includes preliminary notes on the characters for Uncle Roger; notes on The Blue Notebook file structure and plot; notes to Fred Truck about setting up the ACEN datanet version as well as the UNIX shell version; and drafts of the original text for Terminals (File 3). Also includes some notes from an unfinished story, and draft emails regarding an article for the Whole Earth Review.
  - its name was Penelope, 1988-1989, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    3 notebooks and 1 notebook cover with drafts and programming notes from the development of Penelope. Includes changes made following the Richmond Art Center Show in 1989, as well as programming notes for Song, the last file of the piece.
  - Brown House Kitchen, 1993-1994 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    Undated notebook for the work created in LambdaMoo while working for the Xerox PARC as an artist-in-residence. Unfolding insert is a plot of how the food served keyed the narrative. Second notebook, dated 1993-1994, mainly includes the manuals used by Malloy to learn the programming language.
  - Every Luminous Landscape, 2008 (Box 3)
  - Interlude-Dorothy and Sid, published in The Blue Moon Review, Fall 2001 (Box 3)
- Early Artists Books, 1976-1990, (3 boxes)
  Slides, photocopies, and supporting material from some of Malloy's artists books. Includes a small amount of original art.
  - Slides (Box 3)
    Color slides with photographs of Malloy's art and artists books. Descriptions below include the format of each piece, the title, and the date. Some slides cover materials from the Exhibitions and Writings and Programming series.
    - Various slides, 1976-1991 (Box 3)
    - Electromechanical book, Channel, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Electromechanical book, I don't care if I never get back, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Card catalog, Hearst Strip, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Photobook, Array, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Card Catalog, The TV Blew Up, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Card Catalog, A Party in Woodside, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Installation detail showing artists books, Technical Information, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Newspapers, Installation detail, Technical Information, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Artists file, OKGE Files, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Artists book, New Years Eve, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Sculptural artists book, Bad Information, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Illuminated manuscript, I Never Get Jealous, 1984 (Box 3)
    - Sculptural artists book, Free Values, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Sculptural artists book, Germany, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Sculptural artists book, Romeo and Juliet, 1986, (2 slides) (Box 3)
    - Sculptural artists book, Lucy Comes Back, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Sculptural artists book, Free Values, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Slide viewer sculture, Souvenir, 1988 (Box 3)
  - What I Did on my Summer Vacation, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Bedtime, circa 1976 (Box 3)
  - Map, circa 1976 (Box 3)
    Original is pen and ink on a large sheet of ricepaper, which was then folded like a map, with a folder made for it.
  - March at Last, circa 1976 (Box 3)
    Original piece that is a quilt made from Xeroxes of drawings.
  - Bang, circa 1980 (Box 3)
  - Compost, 1980 (Box 11)
    Photo and drawings artists book; an example of the work that inspired the work done by the narrator of its name was Penelope. Two editions were made, the first of which was given to the friends who were in the book.
  - Artist Book statements, 1984-1987 and undated (Box 11)